Chapter 13.
The fourth planet belonged to a businessman.
This man was so much preoccupied that he did not even raise his head at the
little prince's arrival.
"Good morning," the little prince said to him. "Your cigarette has gone out."
"Three and two make five. Five and seven make twelve. Twelve and three make
fifteen. Good morning. Fifteen and seven make twenty two twenty two and six make
Twenty Eight I haven't uh time to light it again 26 and 5 make 31.
fewer Then that makes 501 million six hundred twenty two thousand seven hundred thirty one
500 million watt ask the little print huh Are you still there
501 million I I can't stop... I have so much to do I'm concerned with matters of
consequence. I don't amuse myself with bold and Ash Two and five mix seven
501 million what?" repeated the little prince, who never in his life had let go
of a question once he had asked it.
The businessman raised his head.
"During the 54 years that I've inhabited this planet I've been disturbed only three times.
The first time was 22 years ago and some giddy goose fell from goodness knows
where. He made the most frightful noise that resounded all over the place, and I
made four mistakes in my Edition The second time 11 years ago, I was
disturbed by an attack of rheumatism. I don't get enough exercise. I have no time for loathing
The third time-- well, this is it!
I was saying, then 501 millions--" "Millions of what?"
The businessman suddenly realized that there was no hope of being left in peace
until he answered this question.
"Millions of those little objects," he said, "which one sometimes sees in the sky."
"Flies?"
"Oh, no. Little glittering objects."
"Bees?" "Oh, no. Little golden objects that set lazy men to idle dreaming. As for me
I'm concerned with matters of consequence. There is no time for idle dreaming in my life
Oh You mean the stars?" "Yes, that's it. The stars."
"And what do you do with 500 millions of stars 501 622 731.
I'm concerned with matters of consequence: I am accurate."
"And what do you do with these stars?"
"What do I do with them?"
"Yes." "Nothing. I own them."
"You own the stars?" "Yes I've already seen a king who--" "Kings do
not own, they reign over this is a very different matter."
"And what good does it do you to own the stars
might just be the good of making me rich what good does it do you to be rich?"
"It makes it possible for me to buy more stars, if they are discovered."
"This man," the little prince said to himself, "reasons like my poor tippler..."
Nevertheless, he still had some more questions.
"How is it possible for one to own the stars?"
"To whom do they belong?"
the businessman retorted, peevishly.
"I don't know.
To nobody."
"Then they belong to me, because I was the first person to think of it."
"Is that all that is necessary?"
"Certainly. When you find a diamond that belongs to nobody that is yours. When you
discover an island that belongs to nobody, it is yours. When you get an idea
before anyone else, you take out a patent on it then it is yours.
So with me: I own the stars, because nobody else before me ever thought of owning them."
"Yes, that is true," said the little prince.
"And what do you do with them?"
"I administer them reply the businessman.
"I count them and recount them that is difficult.
But I'm a man who is naturally interested in matters of consequence."
The little prince was still not satisfied.
"If I owned a silk scarf," he said, "I could
put it around my neck and take it away with me. If I owned a flower, I could
pluck that flower and take it away with me. But you cannot pluck the stars from
heaven..." "No. But I can put them in the bank."
"Whatever does that mean?" "That means that I write the number of my stars on a little paper.
And then I put this paper in a drawer and lock it with a key."
"And that is all?"
"That is enough," said the businessman.
"It is entertaining," thought the little prince.
"It is rather poetic.
But it is of no great consequence."
On matters of consequence, the little prince had ideas which were very
different from those of the grown-ups.
"I myself own a flower," he continued his conversation with the
businessman, "which I water every day.
I own three volcanoes, which I clean out every week but I also clean out the one
that is extinct; one never knows it's as of some use to my volcanoes, and it is of
some use to my flower, that I own them two are of no use to the stars..."
The businessman opened his mouth, but he found nothing to say in answer.
And the little prince went away
grown-ups are certainly all together extraordinary," he said simply murmuring to himself
as he continued on his journey